开头8秒的防不胜防，就不翻译了
This video was made possible by Squarespace.
有兴趣看下面链接吧
Build your beautiful website for 10% off at squarespace.com/Wendover.
想象一条铁路线，能9小时内从华盛顿特区到德州的达拉斯……
Imagine a train that took you from Washington, DC to Dallas, Texas in nine hours…
或者9小时内从法国巴黎到雅典……
or Paris, France to Athens, Greece in nine hours…
或者9小时内从南澳洲的阿德莱德到西澳洲的珀斯
or Adelaide, South Australia to Perth, Western Australia in nine hours.
而这些铁路线实际需要44小时、44小时、41小时
These train trips actually take 44 hours, 44 hours, and 41 hours respectively
所以让火车在9小时内完成这些旅途简直天方夜谭
so the idea of making any of these trips by train in nine hours seems almost absurd.
但在中国，这却是家常便饭
In China, though, that’s reality.
2018年9月，中国开通了一条新的高铁线路
In September 2018, the country opened up a brand new high speed rail route
从香港直达北京
with direct trains from Hong Kong to Beijing.
距离和达拉斯到华盛顿特区、巴黎到雅典、阿德莱德到珀斯差不多
This is about the same distance as DC to Dallas, Paris to Athens, or Adelaide to Perth
而该线路全程只需8小时56分钟
and yet these trains make the trip in only 8 hours and 56 minutes.
更牛逼的是，十年前的2008年，北京还在开奥运会的时候
What makes this even more impressive is that ten years ago, in 2008, at the time of the Beijing Olympics
中国高铁线路这有这些
China’s high-speed rail network consisted of this.
我们甚至得放大才能看清，一条是30公里的磁悬浮线路
We’ll have to zoom in because the extent of the network was one 19 mile-long Maglev train
从上海浦东国际机场到上海城区边缘
from Shanghai Airport to the outskirts of Shanghai
和一条北京到天津的高铁线路
and a traditional high-speed rail line from Beijing to the coastal city of Tianjin.
十年后的今天，中国高铁网络变成了这样
Today, ten years later, that network has expanded into this.
中国高铁线路全长是发过的8倍，日本的10倍
China has 8 times as much high speed track as France, 10 times as much as Japan,
英国的20倍，美国的500倍
20 times as much as the UK, and 500 times as much as the US.
实际上，中国的高铁线路长度比其他国家的加一起还要长
In fact, China has as much high-speed rail track as the rest of the world combined.
中国竟然能在短短十年内取得如此伟大的成就
It is staggering the amount of progress they have made in such a short amount of time.
传统的高铁只存在于小的富有的国家，比如德国法国日本
Traditionally high speed rail exists in small countries with rich populations by the likes of Germany, France, and Japan.
中国既不小也不富有
China is neither of these things.
中国很大，和美国差不多，也一点不富有
The country is enormous, about the same size as the US, and is also not rich.
虽然不算贫穷，但中国只是一个中等收入国家
While no longer poor, China is definitively a middle income country.
和墨西哥、泰国、巴西差不多
It’s about as rich as Mexico, Thailand, or Brazil.
事实上，尽管身为世界上拥有高铁里程最多的国家
In fact, despite being the country with the most high speed rail in the world,
中国却是拥有高铁的国家里最穷的
China is also the poorest country in the world to have any high speed rail.
虽然中国很大，但东部的人口密度却非常高
Despite the country’s vast size, China’s huge population makes it very dense especially in the east half.
所以中国的确有很多大型城市群
This means that China does have large cities close enough together
就很适合乘火车在城市群内通勤
where it makes sense to take the train rather than the plane.
而比如广州到长沙，560公里，飞机1小时，高铁2小时20分钟
Trips like Guangzhou to Changsha, a distance of 350 miles, take an hour by plane or 2 hours and 20 minutes by train.
但算上飞机的值机、安检等等程序
When factoring in the time it takes to check in, go through security, and board
坐火车在这两个城市旅行其实是很不错的选择
it absolutely makes sense to go by train when traveling between these two cities
更不用说（多数时候）高铁比机票便宜
even without considering that the high-speed train is cheaper than flying.
对于更长的路线，高铁在中国也很不错，这在其他国家就行不通
High speed rail even makes sense in China on longer routes where it wouldn’t in other countries.
比如北京到上海，1050公里
Beijing and Shanghai, for example, are about 650 miles apart.
正常对于高铁来说距离就太远了
Normally that would be too far for high speed rail to make sense.
巴黎到巴塞罗那，距离和北京到上海差不多
Paris and Barcelona, for example, are 500 miles apart—closer than Beijing and Shanghai
每天只有两次高铁，飞机却有20班
—but only two high speed trains a day run between the two cities compared to about 20 flights.
而北京到上海，每天50班飞机、41次高铁
Between Beijing and Shanghai, on the other hand, about 50 flights run per day run compared to 41 trains.
加之火车拉的人更多，可以达到1200人
Considering the trains carry far more people each, up to 1,200,
因此火车才是承担两地客流的主要支柱
trains are therefore the dominant means of transport between these two cities.
而京沪、巴黎巴塞罗那两条线路之间还有些区别
There are a few differences between these two routes.
首先，京沪线耗时4小时28分
For one, while Beijing-Shanghai by train takes 4 hours and 28 minutes,
巴黎到巴塞罗那，虽然距离更短，但却耗时6小时25分
Paris-Barcelona, despite being a shorter distance, takes a longer 6 hours and 25 minutes.
另外一个不同是航空业的竞争
The other factor, though, is about the competition.
欧洲的民航网络非常发达，机票远远比火车票便宜
Europe has an efficient air transport network dominated by budget airlines that are often far cheaper than trains.
巴黎到巴塞罗那机票也就12刀
You can find tickets for flights between Paris and Barcelona for as little as $12
但最便宜的京沪线机票却要74刀
while the cheapest Beijing-Shanghai flights go for $74.
中国的民航真的太辣鸡
Air travel within China is also far from efficient.
中国三大航：南航、东航、国航
China Southern, China Eastern, and Air China, the three largest Chinese airlines,
准点率分别是67%，66%，63%
arrive on time an average of 67%, 66%, and 63% of the time respectively.
其重要原因是空域太少
A big reason for this is that there’s just not enough room in the skies.
中国空域绝大多数都归军方管制
A majority of China’s airspace is military controlled
使得大约只有30%的狭窄空域是给民航使用的
meaning that there are just these narrow flight corridors that account for 30% of airspace where civilian planes can fly.
大量的飞机挤在如此狭小的空域
With tons of planes and not much room to fly
导致大量飞机因为等待管制放行而延误
planes are frequently delayed by air traffic control to wait for the airspace to clear up
从而导致中国的航司准点率如此之惨
which leads to the abysmal on-time ratings of the country’s airlines.
所以虽说飞京沪线只要两小时
While the Beijing-Shanghai flight takes only two hours,
但潜在的延误、加上其他各种因素，导致坐飞机真不快
the potential of delays, along with all the other factors that make air travel slower,
也使得高铁成为人们更青睐的交通工具
help make the train the popular means of transport on this longer route.
但中国其他高铁线路就让人看不懂了
Other train routes in China, though, make less sense.
比如在2014年新开通了一条兰州到乌鲁木齐的高铁线路
For example, in 2014, the new high speed train line opened between Lanzhou and Urumqi.
这俩城市在中国都不算大城市
These two cities are relatively small by China standards.
都有350万人口，沿途全是小镇子
They both have a population of 3.5 million and between them are only small towns.
离得也特远，相距1600公里
They’re also not close—about 1,000 miles separate them.
相当于在美国建一条从丹佛到西雅图的高铁
This project could therefore be compared to building a high speed train from Denver to Seattle
这俩也是中等城市，离得很远，中间也没有大城市
—they’re modestly sized cities a long way’s apart with nothing big in between.
或许会有人坐，但绝对没法挣钱
Some people would use it but it wouldn’t make any financial sense.
在中国，兰州和鸟市不算小，但中间也真没大城市
In China, Lanzhou and Urumqi are not small cities but there’s really nothing big in between
而且这个距离也实在想不出不坐飞机的理由
and, at that distance, there’s no sense not flying.
兰州到鸟市，高铁耗时11小时，飞机只要两个半小时
The Lanzhou-Urumqi high speed train takes 11 hours compared to the 2.5 hour flight
高铁造价200亿刀
and the construction cost of that line was $20 billion
说明如果每列高铁都坐满
meaning that if every seat on every train was filled
单程票价需要达到400刀才能在30年内收回建造成本
tickets would still have to cost $400 each way just to make back the construction cost in 30 years.
实际票价只有80刀，且根本坐不满
In reality tickets cost about $80 and trains are far from full
说明这线路完全是在赔本运行
meaning that this rail line is just insanely far from profitable.
票价带来的收入连线路电费都不够
The ticket revenues from these trains reportedly don’t even cover the cost of electricity for the line
更不要说建造成本和其它运营成本
let alone construction and other operating costs.
那为什么中国政府如此下血本造一条根本不可能挣钱的高铁线路呢？
So why would the Chinese government sink so much money into something that has no prospects of really ever making money?
答案是政治原因
Well, politics.
鸟市是新疆维吾尔自治区的首府
Urumqi is the capital of the Xinjiang province.
92%的中国人是汉族，而新疆有很多的维吾尔族
While 92% of China’s population is Han Chinese, the Xinjiang province is primarily Uyghur
维族是中国少数民族之一
—one of the minority ethnic groups of China
那边一直有很强的分裂势力，曾经常弄出暴力事件
—and there has been an ongoing fairly strong separatist movement by the Uyghurs from China that has often turned violent.
北京则想让新疆和国家其余部分那样同化
The central government in Beijing, however, wants the Xinjiang province to be just as integrated as the rest of the country
并采取了很多强制措施
and has tried a variety of methods to force this
比如送很多汉人进入自治区、送一些维族进所谓的“再教育营”
including moving Han Chinese into the region and the imprisonment of Uyghurs in so-called “reeducation camps.”
修高铁也是最新的、让新疆离首都更近的一种手段罢了，不是啥秘密
The high-speed train is just the most recent tactic to bring Xinjiang closer to Beijing and this is no secret.
政府一直在说修这条线路是为了促进民族团结
The central government is fully upfront in saying that the line was built to promote, as they call it, “ethnic unity.”
这也不是中国第一次用铁路作为政治手段了
This isn’t even the first time they’ve used this tactic of railroad politics.
西藏，和新疆一样也有一股分裂势力
Tibet, a region even better known than Xinjiang for its independence movement,
是中国最后一个没有通铁路的省份，因为那里人口少、地形复杂
was the last region in China not to have a railway due to its small population and intense terrain.
中央决定修一条铁路拉近西藏与首都的距离，于是青藏铁路诞生了
The central government still wanted to build one, though, to bring it closer to the rest of the country and so they did.
如今火车可以在47小时内从北京到拉萨，开上全世界海拔最高的铁路
Trains now run directly from Beijing to Lhasa, Tibet in 47 hours on the highest elevation rail line in the world.
海拔可达5071米，高到乘客需要氧气供应
These trains reach an elevation of 16,640 feet—so high that passengers have to use a direct oxygen supply.
而北京到香港的高铁也是中央为了拉近香港的距离
Even the train to Hong Kong serves the central government’s goal of further integrating Hong Kong
香港和中国大陆不同，是一个特别行政区
which is an autonomous special administrative region, into mainland China.
虽说北京到香港的高铁比兰州鸟市高铁更能让人理解
While high-speed trains to Hong Kong certainly do make a lot more sense than trains to the Xinjiang province
很多香港人却也不欢迎它来
many Hong Kongers have not greeted the new service kindly
他们认为这是对香港基本法的侵犯
as they view it as an encroachment on the autonomy guaranteed to them by Hong Kong Basic Law.
最有争议的其实不是火车
The most controversial part has not been the fact that there’s a train
而是在香港的那站里现在有一部分归中国大陆了
but rather that the station in Hong Kong includes an area that is effectively now part of Mainland China
人们在香港上火车之前要先过边检了
since people pass through border controls before boarding the train in Hong Kong.
和其他国家类似，中国修建高铁网络的目的
Just like any country, what having a high-speed, efficient rail network in China is doing
就是把让国家更加统一更加强大
is bringing the country together and making it stronger
即使有些地方的人还想搞分裂
even if it’s bringing together people that want to stay apart.
不管目的如何
No matter their motives,
中国建造高铁的效率是比其他任何国家都快的
it’s clear that China is building their high speed rail network more efficiently than any other country.
作为对比，这是加州旧金山到洛圣都的高铁规划
To compare, this is the plan for California’s high speed rail line from San Francisco to the Los Angeles area.
其目前还在建设的最初阶段，预计2029年通车
It’s currently in very early phases of construction and is expected to open by 2029.
说明加州建完这一条线路的时间
Of course that means that the time it will take for the California’s high speed rail network to go from this to this
和中国建完全国高铁网络的时间差不多
is the same as the time it took China’s high speed rail network to go from this to this
同时注意下造价
But, the main thing to look at is cost.
加州高铁预计造价770亿刀，520英里长
This Californian network is expected to cost $77 billion and is 520 miles long
平均每英里1.48亿刀
meaning that it will cost $148 million per mile to build.
而中国的高铁网络，平均每英里造价只有3000万刀
China, on the other hand, is building their network at a cost of only $30 million per mile.
当然中国的劳动力比较便宜，且铁路所经之处比较偏远，地价不高
Of course labor costs are lower in China and their network crosses more rural areas where land acquisition costs are lower
但中国最牛逼的是他们把高铁建设几乎变成了一条生产线
But, what’s more meaningful is that they’ve turned building high speed rail into almost an assembly line process
从而让高架桥、隧道等很多造价高昂的基建量产化
where they can mass produce even the most expensive elements like viaducts and tunnels.
中国正在让高铁变得廉价化
In true Chinese fashion, with scale they’re making high-speed cheaper.
中国与其他西方国家最大的不同
The big difference between China and a lot of the western world,
——尤其是像美国、加拿大、澳大利亚、新西兰、英国
particularly countries like the US, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, and the UK,
——是中国政府把高铁建设摆在首位
is that high speed rail is at the top of the government’s priorities.
在很多方面，中国政府都会把社会利益
Unsurprisingly given their government structure, in many ways, China has placed social benefit,
——至少是他们定义的“社会价值”
at least by the definition of the central government,
——放在单纯的线路利润之前
ahead of profitability when developing their high speed rail network.
高铁线路可能利润不如飞机等其他交通工具多
High-speed rail lines just aren’t as profitable as other means of transport like planes
但它毫无疑问对国家是有利的
but they are undoubtably better for countries
所以当你考虑其总体利润的时候，一定要算上其带来的社会利益
so you have to consider the social benefit when looking at their overall profitability.
比如之前说的加州高铁线路
For the San Francisco to LA high speed rail route, for example,
一项研究发现，这条线路所降低的碳排放、所提高的生产力
one study found that the social benefit derived from lower carbon emissions, higher worker productivity,
和所减少的公路致命事故的损失可达每年4.4亿刀
and reduced casualties from fewer people on the road would be equivalent to about $440 million per year.
结果，这和政府扶持线路建设的钱基本扯平了
As it turns out, this is almost the exact amount that the state will have to subsidize the line for it to break even.
中国铁路总公司作为一个国有企业，挣的钱不但不多
The China Railway Corporation, a state owned enterprise, is actually slightly profitable,
还有很多外债，还要靠国家的扶持
although it does have huge amounts of debts and is helped by government subsidies.
但高铁对全中国人民带来的利益，是非常巨大的
The benefit to the Chinese people, though, is huge.
高铁让在花销高昂的北上广打拼的人们
The high-speed rail allows those who can’t afford to live in the most expensive cities like Beijing, Shanghai, and Guangzhou
能够轻松乘高铁去其他城市
to easily commute from cheaper suburbs by high-speed rail.
也多亏了高铁，7500万人可以在一小时内坐高铁去上海
Thanks to the high-speed rail, there are now 75 million people who can commute to Shanghai in under an hour.
原本就很大的城市更是如虎添翼，而对于城市来说，规模就是力量
It is growing what are already some of the largest cities and, when it comes to cities, size is strength.
这些东部城市的高铁线路是全世界最赚钱的铁路线路
These lines connecting the east’s largest cities are some of the most profitable rail lines in the world
也让在中国居住、工作的人们生活更加便利
and they’re making living and working in China easier.
下一个问题是，回顾过去几十年，高铁途径小城市将来是否有意义？
But the question is, when we look back decades from now, whether the high-speed trains to smaller cities will have made sense?
因为要在大城市间尽量走直线
Out of a desire to keep the lines going straight between the big cities,
高铁途径的几个小城市的车站通常离市中心很远的郊区
the stops for smaller cities are often out in the countryside dozens of miles away from the city core.
衡阳——一百万人口的小城市——的高铁站
The high speed station for Hengyang, for example, a smaller city of only a million,
在市中心45分钟车程的西边
is about a 45 minute drive east of the city center.
虽然城市希望未来以车站为中心发展
The hope is that new development will spring up around the stations
但这样的网络结构，即使在火车上省了时间
but this network structure, even if it saves time on the train,
却在前后去车站的路上浪费了，这又降低了高铁的效益
wastes time before and after which degrades the benefit of high-speed rail.
总之，中国是世界上第一个
In all, China is really the first country to have experimented
长距离穿越其西部人口稀少地区的国家
with long-distance, high speed rail through less-dense areas in its west.
而在东部，高铁则推动了全国的经济发展
In the east, though, these trains are enlarging the country’s economic power.
而这也只是中国追赶其他发达国家的方法之一
It’s just one of the many factors speeding up China’s catch-up with world’s richest countries.
尽管中国正在以较小的速度建造列车，并在高铁建设方面进行创新
Even though China is building these trains for less and innovating on the construction of high-speed rail
中国如此擅长建造高铁的真正原因
the real reason why China is so good at building railways is because
是他们有建造高铁的政治需求——这是其他国家没有的
they have the one thing that almost every other country lacks—the political will for high-speed trains.
字幕翻译给虫 欢迎点赞投币收藏转发分享关注充电评论
依然是防不胜防时间 链接在下面
squarespace.com/Wendover